♪ ♪
Alone, inexperienced,
life has never been tougher
for this young orangutan.
She will have to go
to extraordinary lengths
to find enough food.
A third of her kind will fall
and break bones or worse.
In this hostile world,
only the strongest
make it to the top.
Torrential rain, tropical heat
and the relentless assault of insects.
If you're not prepared,
the jungle will eat you alive.
But these conditions
have created a home
for more species than anywhere else
on the planet.
You might think
it's an animal Eden,
but it's more like
a wildlife war zone.
Now that the rains, the lifeblood
of these extraordinary worlds,
are becoming more unpredictable,
the battle for survival
has never been fiercer.
Even rainforests have dry seasons.
Rivers become the focus
of jungle life.
A jaguar,
South America's apex predator.
Jaguars will hunt anything
from a vulture to an anaconda.
But nothing's guaranteed.
It's been days since she's eaten.
Jaguars are the most aquatic
of all big cats.
She'll have more success
in the water.
Capybara.
A big opportunity.
There are other options,
but there's also competition.
A male.
He's hunted here
for over a decade,
taking on dangerous prey
and other jaguars.
Life here isn't getting
any easier.
As dry seasons become more extreme,
competition for prey increases.
Better for her to hunt
in less contested waters
where prehistoric killers
lie waiting
to drag their victims under.
With each step,
a trap could snap shut.
With the right bite,
she'll pierce skull
and immobilize it.
But this caiman is much more
than a mouthful.
♪ ♪
A kill this big
has rarely been recorded.
It will feed her for days.
For other animals, finding food
at the height
of the dry season
is much more of a struggle.
Fruit makes up around 60%
of this young orangutan's diet.
To survive, she must form
a complex mental map
of where and when to find it.
This takes years.
Up here,
there's nothing but leaves.
Rainfall has dropped by a third.
And droughts are more frequent.
How can she predict
where to find food
when the world around her
keeps changing?
The more she searches,
the more she risks.
♪ ♪
Far below on the forest floor,
only 2% of sunlight penetrates.
It's not water that limits life;
it's light.
For every 100,000 seeds,
only one will survive.
Fewer still will ever
reach the canopy.
They have to fight
for their place in the sun.
Just half an inch can mean
the difference between life and death.
Each plant has its own strategy
to get ahead.
This struggle makes the jungle
one of the most competitive
environments on Earth.
A war in which every leaf matters.
In the dry season,
there's not much else to eat.
Plants fight back
with spikes and poison,
loading their leaves with toxin.
With each bite, their victims
become sicker and sicker.
There is an antidote,
but to reach it
they must face the jungle's
most dangerous predators.
Poisoned by the plants they eat,
these animals must reach
the antidote.
But it's a dangerous mission.
Ocelot, jaguars, and puma
are waiting.
A deadly game of hide and seek,
and at its heart,
a most unlikely cure: clay.
It's rich in the minerals and salts
needed to neutralize the toxins.
But the longer the dry season,
the more they must visit the clay.
♪ ♪
With so much danger
on the forest floor,
it pays to keep off the ground.
This orangutan spends 90%
of her time in the trees.
As the heaviest arboreal species
in the world,
orangutans let their weight
do the work.
Tree swaying saves half the energy
she would normally use to climb.
Shortage of food
in the dry season
forces her to rest more.
Each afternoon she makes her bed,
weaving branches into a nest
that will keep her safe
through the night.
And these trees provide more
than food and shelter.
Remarkably, they also help create
the jungle's weather.
By the end of the dry season,
the sun is at its most intense.
Trees pump out more water vapor
than at any other time of year.
In this jungle,
almost 20 billion tons every day.
All this water creates
the wet season here.
But this jungle is shrinking,
and its rainmaking power is fading.
Every decade the change
from dry to wet
comes a week later.
A mighty storm is brewing,
but before it strikes,
there's a killing to be made.
Competition for food is so intense
during the day,
it has forced some creatures
into the night.
Spectral tarsiers.
To thrive in the dark,
they've evolved eyes
bigger than their brains,
and the best night vision
of any primate.
But they still need
a little help: a moon.
When it's full,
this family can catch more,
so they hunt for twice as long.
♪ ♪
But when storm clouds
obscure the moon,
others are better equipped
to kill in the shadows.
This python sees with heat
and smells with taste.
The tables turn again.
Living in a group means
these tarsiers
can look out for each other.
♪ ♪
With no element of surprise,
the python has no chance.
But life is about to get tougher.
The wet season has arrived,
and it's hitting harder than ever.
Before the wet season breaks,
there are more lightning strikes
in jungles
than anywhere else on Earth.
By 2050, some estimate
they will increase by a third.
The storms these trees help create
can also be their downfall.
♪ ♪
The death of an emergent tree
is an essential part
of the cycle of life.
The increased humidity
during the wet season
sets off a chain reaction.
Fungi and slime molds
race to decompose
dead matter on the forest floor.
Rot and decay run rampant
faster than anywhere else on Earth.
In some jungles, species of fungi
outnumber plants 33 to 1.
As they feed on the dead,
they recycle critical nutrients
which the forest uses to grow.
Many spread by releasing spores,
up to 30,000 a second.
If just one of these spores lands
in the right place
and takes root,
it can colonize a whole new area.
But not all fungi feed on the dead.
Days ago,
a spore landed on this ant.
Now she's acting strange.
A network of roots
has infiltrated her muscles.
Her body has been taken over
by Cordyceps,
a parasitic fungus.
It floods her brain
with chemicals,
drugging her, compelling her
to head
where conditions are perfect.
Just the right amount of light,
just the right amount of humidity
for the parasite growing inside.
It forces her to clamp down
in a death bite,
and Cordyceps reveals
its gruesome nature.
After 3 weeks of growth,
Cordyceps can release
its own spores,
infecting more ants,
releasing more spores,
more and more and more.
Cordyceps can wipe out
entire ant colonies.
But more than just ants
are at risk.
There are over 600 species
of Cordyceps
spread across the world.
Most are found in jungles
where they prey on
a whole host of victims.
♪ ♪
The wet season brings a flush
of fruit to the canopy.
Lar gibbons must move fast
before it's all gone.
They fly through the trees
at 35 miles an hour,
even with a baby on board.
They can cover 40 ft
in a single leap.
But they don't get it right
every time.
This family of lar gibbons
lives in a dangerous world.
Their forest is being fragmented.
One day they may face a jump
they can't quite make.
Food is harder to find
as a wet season grows more erratic.
And when the rain comes,
it can fall in shorter,
more intense bursts.
If it's too wet,
it's best to sit tight.
This orangutan has learned
a lot from her mother:
how to make a jungle umbrella.
It comes in handy
in the rainiest environment on Earth.
For many animals,
heavy rain stops activity.
But for some,
that's not an option.
This male booted racket-tail
hummingbird
lives on the brink
of starvation.
Just two hours without nectar
and he could die.
Hummingbirds have
the fastest metabolisms on Earth.
Some need to visit
2,000 flowers a day
just to keep going.
This mountainous forest
is one of the few jungles
that is getting wetter.
Heavy rain is predicted
to increase,
and when you weigh
less than a nickel,
raindrops are a bombardment.
Waterlogged feathers
slow his progress.
Staying airborne
becomes more demanding.
But he's running on empty,
and the clock is ticking.
Even during a downpour,
competition for flowers is fierce.
A buff-tailed coronet,
intent on keeping
the nectar-filled flowers
for himself.
The racket-tail is no competition
for the coronet.
He must wait
for another opportunity.
As the rains slow,
over 40 species
fight for their nectar hit.
♪ ♪
With the coronet facing
bigger battles,
this is a racket-tail's chance
to sneak a sip.
It takes more energy to hover
than almost any other activity
on Earth.
We'd have to drink
over a can of soda a minute
to keep up.
Another racket-tail.
Evenly matched,
he won't back down.
Tail splayed, feet forward,
he means business.
♪ ♪
The winner takes all.
But he can't rest.
He still has a lot
of flowers to visit,
and the next downpour
is never far off.
Rainfall in the Andes
transforms life
over a thousand miles away.
So much water collects
in the Amazon basin below
that the Earth's crust
sinks by 3 in.
A drowned forest.
This extreme change takes months.
Even so, it can creep up
on those
who live their life
in slow motion.
Moving between the trees
becomes challenging.
She needs to find her next meal,
but she's surrounded.
Creatures that spend most of the year
on the forest floor
now find themselves floating
30 ft above it.
Their only refuge
is in the trees.
But she must brave the deep.
This sloth's home is flooded.
To find her food,
she must swim,
defenseless against
what lies beneath.
♪ ♪
Like most animals here,
sloths are adapted
to get through
this annual flood.
Fermenting leaves fill
her stomach with gas
that helps keep her afloat.
She's three times faster in water
than on land.
When the forest floods,
it opens up a whole new world.
Pink river dolphins can explore
an area larger than Arizona.
They echolocate to hunt for fish
in the murk
using higher frequencies
than their marine cousins
to see with superior definition.
Recently, these floods have been
reaching record-breaking highs,
but there have also been
devastating lows.
And as our world changes,
drought is the greatest natural threat
to jungles worldwide.
Australia was once covered
by a jungle
larger than the Amazon rainforest.
Now barely 1% survives,
clinging to what little water remains.
And little red flying foxes
cling on with it.
It's a 104°F.
Just 4° more, and this male
will die of heat shock.
He needs to escape the sun.
But with hundreds of thousands
of bats in the colony,
the shadiest spots are hard won.
Exposed,
he's dangerously dehydrating.
The river is their only salvation,
but it can also be their ruin.
These waters are infested
with freshwater crocodiles.
Better to stay away.
Try and hold out till nightfall.
But with every breath,
he loses more water.
More and more bats
give in to their thirst,
and he won't last much longer.
It's safer to share the risk.
To collect water, they must dip
their fur in the river,
but no one wants to be first.
♪ ♪
Safe.
But he must brave this river
every day
until the rains arrive.
Over the next 50 years,
it could get too hot
and dry for this colony
to survive at all.
Could this be the future
for jungles around the world?
These amazing forests
not only create oxygen and rain
that nourish our planet;
they're also home to a greater
diversity of animals
than anywhere else on Earth.
These creatures
are super specialized
to survive all the complexities
of life in the jungle.
But in times of change, that also
leaves them highly vulnerable.
It takes years for an orangutan
to learn
how to find its way
in these forests,
and today's changing climate
makes life even tougher.
And that isn't all
she has to contend with.
Rainforests around the world
are disappearing faster
than ever before.
Her future, like that
of all jungle life,
has never been less certain.
♪ ♪